A Guide to the Alexander and James M. Donnan papers, 1835-1892
Library of Virginia
Library of Virginia
Alexander and James M. Donnan papers, 1835-1892
The Library of Virginia
51763
.225 cu. ft. and 1 box
Alexander and James M. Donnan
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
There are no restrictions.
Acquisition Information
Purchased from Cowan's Auctions, Inc., Cincinnati, Ohio.
Biographical Information
Alexander Donnan was born 21 May 1818 in Dumfries, Scotland, the sixth child of David Donnan (1778-1857) and Mary Stewart Donnan (1787-1850). The family migrated to Virginia, where the Donnans' ninth child, James Monroe Donnan, was born 6 May 1824 in Amelia County, Virginia. Alexander and James M. Donnan moved to Petersburg, Virginia, where they practiced law together. Alexander Donnan married Anne Eliza Willson (1827-1912), and they had six children. Alexander Donnan died 14 March 1892 in Petersburg, and was buried in Blandford Cemetery. James M. Donnan was an avowed Unionist during the Civil War and a Radical Republican during Reconstruction. He served on the Petersburg City Council and was United States Consul at Belfast, Ireland, from 1873 to 1880. He was married three times: first, to Virginia Hubbard; second, to Mary H. Williams; and third, to Annie Thompson, who died on 16 November 1910. James Donnan died on 14 January 1893 in Richmond, Virginia, and was buried at Blandford Cemetery in Petersburg.
Scope and Content
Papers, 1835-1892, of Alexander Donnan and James M. Donnan, lawyers in Petersburg, Virginia, consisting of accounts, almanacs, checks, correspondence, deeds, envelopes and wrappers, forms, funeral announcements, insurance policies, judicial records, powers of attorney, promissory notes, receipts, and other papers. Papers involve the legal work of the Donnans' law firm, including the hire or sale of slaves, legal proceedings, tax payments, and pensions for veterans of the War of 1812.
Contents List
- Letter, 22 September 1835, from Charles Rogers of Petersburg, Virginia, to Stewart and Fountain of Columbus, Georgia, recommending J. W. Adams for a position in their factory. (Folder 1)
- Letter, 11 August 1857, from Berthier Bott of Dinwiddie County, Virginia, to Alexander and James M. Donnan, Petersburg, regarding his debts and their payment. (Folder 2)
- Letter, 30 November 1857, from Dr. William F. Thompson of Dinwiddie County to Berthier Bott, Dinwiddie County, regarding the health of Bott's slaves that are to be sold. (Folder 2)
- Insurance policy, 31 December 1858, from the Mutual Assurance Society of Virginia to Charles Kent of Petersburg for a structure owned by Kent. (Folder 3)
- List, 26 December 1861, of slaves to be hired out for the estate of G. B. Morgan, Petersburg. List was made by S. C. Morgan who sent it to Thomas Wallace, asking him to forward it to Alexander and James M. Donnan. (Folder 4)
- Letter, 26 December 1861, from Peter C. Marks of Prince George County, Virginia, to Alexander Donnan, Petersburg, regarding the hiring out of a female slave. (Folder 5)
- Letter, 30 December 1861, from Maria Bragg, Petersburg, to Alexander and James M. Donnan regarding the hiring out of Jane, Sally, and Louisa. (Folder 6)
- Letter, 31 December 1861, from Alexander and James M. Donnan, Petersburg, to Samuel H., Marks, Petersburg, asking if Marks will hire Colin. Letter includes Marks' reply. (Folder 7)
- Letter, 14 January 1861 [1862], from M. Debrill, Henrico County, Virginia, to Mr. Donnan, Petersburg, concerning her slaves Randall, Cilia, and their children and their hiring out. (Folder 8)
- Letter, 26 December 1864, from Sylvia Turner, Amelia County, Virginia, to M. Debrill, Henrico County, stating that she cannot keep Debrill's slaves Randall, Cilia, and their children any longer. (Folder 8)
- Letter, 14 January 1862, from F. A. Carnis[?] to Mr. Donnan, Petersburg, regarding a claim. (Folder 9)
- letter, 1 November 1862, from Field A. Clay, Nottoway County, Virginia, to Alexander Donnan, Petersburg, asking for a valuation of slaves. (Folder 10)
- Statement, 20 November 1862, of George Davis regarding the prices of slaves in March-April 1842. (Folder 11)
- Petition, 22 May 1863, of J. A. Johnston, guardian of the children of Samuel H. Whitmore to the Petersburg Circuit Court. (Folder 12)
- Letter, 23 May 1863, from William H. E. Merritt of Brunswick County, Virginia, to [Alexander?] Donnan regarding a problem in the hire of a slave woman and child. (Folder 13)
- Letter and receipt, 8 July 1863, from Mary J. Willcox of Prince George County to Alexander Donnan, Petersburg, for the sale of her slave Minerva. (Folder 14)
- Letter, 23 July 1863, from Mary J. Willcox of Prince George County to Alexander Donnan, Petersburg, regarding the money from the sale of Minerva. (Folder 14)
- List, undated, of slaves from Flowerdew Hundred Plantation in Prince George County. (Folder 14)
- Legal petition, 27 September 1863, of Thomas E. Chambliss of Brunswick County to the Petersburg Circuit Court claiming that he is being illegally held under the conscription act which he considers unconstitutional. (Folder 15)
- Letter, 9 January 1864, from Alexander Donnan[?], Petersburg, to Captain Frank Potts, regarding a slave that is with Jenkins' Brigade. (Folder 16)
- Letter, 10 February 1864, from Lucilla Harrison, [Prince George County?], to Alexander and James M. Donnan, Petersburg, expressing her wishes to sell a slave woman and child. (Folder 17)
- Letter, 10 December [1864?], from Lucilla Harrison, [Prince George County?], to Alexander and James M. Donnan, Petersburg, regarding the hire of a slave woman and child, and Harrison's concerns about securing the money from that hire if Petersburg falls to the Union army. (Folder 17)
- Letter, 18 August 1864, from E. Donnan, Petersburg, to Alexander Donnan, Petersburg, asking that Alexander Donnan sell his slave Harry. (Folder 18)
- Letter, 5 November 1864, from Winny Pettiway, Petersburg, to Colonel David Potts, Petersburg, regarding her efforts to recover slaves who have left. (Folder 19)
- Letter, 19 December 1864, from A. J. Leavelle of Sussex County, Virginia, to Alexander Donnan, Petersburg, asking Donnan to rent out his lot. Leavelle adds that the Union army has carried off almost all his slaves. (Folder 20)
- Power of attorney, 11 January 1865, from James Aldridge, Petersburg, to Alexander Donnan, Petersburg, regarding the hire of Aldridge's slave. (Folder 21)
- Division of slaves, undated, of the estate of J. McD. Anderson by Mary J. Wells. (Folder 22)
- General papers, 1845-1892, of Alexander and James M. Donnan, Petersburg, consisting of accounts, almanacs, affidavits, correspondence, deeds, funeral announcements, judicial records, receipts, and warrants relating to the legal affairs of Alexander and James M. Donnan, attorneys. (Folder 22)
- Lunenburg County tax receipts, 1866-1880, for William Turner Blackwell, John A. Roach, O. M. Smith, D. R. Stokes, John H. Stokes, and E. H. Blackwell's estate. (Folder 23)
- Petersburg tax receipts, 1874-1875, for B. F. Cosby. (Folder 23)
- War of 1812 pension papers, 1871, 1873, including some filled out. Some of the forms and correspondece are from Sanborn and King, a law firm in Washington D.C. (Folder 24)
- Receipts and checks, 1855-1874, consisting of checks, receipts, and promissory notes for individuals living in Petersburg for purchase of goods and services, or payment of debts. (Folder 25)
- Promissory note forms, 1856 and undated, one partially filled, rest are blank. (Folder 26)
- Envelopes and wrappers, undated, including one that says Confederate States Treasury Notes. Put away with the sincere hope that they may be good again. Envelopes are empty. (Folder 27)